Michael Penhallegon

Seattle, WA 98144 / (425) 243-9426 / mike@hematite.tech

Summary:

Software developer and data analyst/engineer with a focus on intersection of health/biotechnology and software. Has a diverse skill-sets in technology, application development, creative problem-solving and data analytics to health research and advocacy. Has utilized mixtures of skill-sets to develop projects utilized to transition to a database to maintain contacts, analytically investigate health disparities and most recently, process and maintain data quality of research/clinical trial data.

- 7-years of experience with Python and advanced knowledge of R, Java and SQL
- Developed strong skills in data pipelining and wrangling before and through ETL (extract, transform and load)
- Emerging health researcher, utilizing cross-disciplinary skills to analyze problems and implement solutions

Professional Experience:

Celgene Seattle, WA

Associate Data Scientist

August 2018-Present

- Collaborated with translational science researchers and clinicians on utilizing technology to deliver answers to research questions in clinical trials
- Transitioned and promoted from Research Associate to Associate Data Scientist
- Designed, tested and implemented projects in Python, R and Scala to process, format and ingest clinical trial data into data warehouses and data stores, like Labkey and Hadoop
- Developed and released internally 2 R Packages utilized to process and upload data to a data warehouse.
- Utilized SQL to aggregate and combine data; connect and corelate disparate datasets and maintain data quality.

 Allowing more holistic use of translational medicine research metrics to investigate clinical and research questions

Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center

Seattle, WA

Research Intern, HIV Vaccine Trial Network Core Lab

April 2018-June 2018

- Completed thorough literature review and prepared results for publication in an academic journal.
- Contributed to a qualitative research project investigating HIV/AIDS stigma among HIV+ and HIV- men
- Refactored and published an R package, to linearly interpolate Census-data to generate heath metric values.

Summer Research Intern June 2017-August 2017

- Developed a project in analyzing connections, using R, Python and Tableau, between home value and health disparities in African-American neighborhoods using public census and health data.
- Contributed to a research project to analyze improving retention of minorities in medical trials.

The Evergreen State College

Olympia, WA

Quasr Tutor

September 2017-June 2018

- Tutored mathematics up to differential calculus, discrete mathematics, programming and digital logic
- Learned and used equity-minded pedagogy to tutor and engage students in using quantitative skill sets

Outreach and Retention Advisor, TRiO Student Success

June 2016-June 2018

- Advised and mentored first-generation/low-income students in navigating college and achieving success.
- Assisted linking college administration to students through development of job descriptions, running candidate student forums and recruitment of students to college committees

Stonewall Youth, Olympia, WA

Olympia, WA

Programming Coordinator

October 2015-June 2016

- Developed programming for at-risk LGBTQ youth; Helped maintain drop-in hours for participants
- Developed backup plan; edited and maintained WordPress site including backup and software updates

• Utilized Python and R to clean and restore both participant and donor data. Normalized data from legacy systems.

Peninsula College Port Angeles, WA

Office Assistant, Longhouse Diversity Services

February 2014-June 2014

- Coordinated event management for two large campus-wide events
- Maintained, updated and transitioned tribal contact database from Microsoft Excel to Access

Education:

The Evergreen State College

September 2015-June 2018

Bachelor of Art, emphasis in Computer Science and Public Health Studies

Peninsula College

Janurary 2013-June-2015

Associate of Art, Direct Transfer Agreement/General Studies

Volunteer Experience:

King-Snohomish-Island Counties Ryan White Grant Review Committee, Member, October 2018-December 2018 AIDS Memorial Pathway Project, Committee Volunteer, August 2018-Present

The Evergreen State College Provost Search Committee, Member, September 2016-January 2017

Nomenus, Active Member, June 2009-Present

Skills:

General: 65 wpm, interpersonal skills, customer service, and consensus decision-making. **Computing:** Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Access, Outlook), Tableau. Mac, Windows, and Linux desktop environments. **Programming and Software Development:** Python, R, Java, Scala, git, Jira, HTML/CSS, JQuery, PostgreSQL, MariaDB, test-driven development (TDD)

Professional Memberships

American Public Health Association, 2017-present, Member